In September 2025,
Mr Zhulkarnain Abdul Rahim asked the minister responsible for the PDPA a
simple question. When
someone requests their own CCTV footage under the Personal Data Protection
Act, must the
organisation preserve that footage while the request is being processed?
Minister Josephine Teo’s answer was clear. Yes.
Organisations must have appropriate measures to preserve the requested data.
There are
criminal penalties for intentional destruction to avoid an access request.
That was
said in Parliament on the 22nd of
September 2025. But by then, my
footage had already been deleted. This is what
happened when I made my request. 13th of April 2024.
5:06 in the morning. I was
riding my motorcycle on Cairnhill
Road when a
taxi cut into my lane. The taxi
driver gave the 1st account. He
said I had skidded on my own. I had no
memory to contradict him. The
diagnosis came later: a
subarachnoid haemorrhage. Bleeding
around the brain. I had no
memory of what happened to me. Not the
impact. Not the
minutes before.
Nothing. What I did
know was this:
2 condominiums flanked the
road where the accident happened. Both had
CCTV cameras pointing at the street. When
security guards checked the footage, they
identified it within minutes. They described to me what had
happened. I was then
asked to make a formal request to management. So I did,
starting with The Scotts Tower, because that was the more
direct front view of the accident. The
taxi cutting into my lane was on video. It existed. It was findable. That
footage was the only
record of an event I have no memory of. I needed it for
2 reasons.
1: to understand what happened to me, and to
prove I did not skid on my own.
2: to support an insurance claim against the driver. Both
seemed straightforward. Both were not.
4 days after the accident, I walked into the management office of The
Scotts Tower. I
explained what happened. I asked for the CCTV footage of the road. They
said no. Privacy reasons. I
asked who the data protection officer was. They wouldn’t
tell me. I
asked what company managed the building. They wouldn’t tell me that
either. I asked who I could escalate to. No
answer. I
left the building with no company name, no DPO contact, and no
escalation path. I had to
identify the managing agent myself. I had to
track down the DPO myself. The other
condominium, Suites@Cairnhill,
began differently. Staff there had
allowed me to take a short recording of the CCTV screen. Not through the
PDPA process. Just a
brief recording, because they could see why I needed to understand what
had happened. After PDPC
ignored my request for the more direct front footage from The Scotts Tower,
I
later tried the other angle. I
made a formal request to Suites@Cairnhill for
fuller footage. I did not
say who had helped me earlier. I was
trying to protect the staff. The
managing agent’s DPO then refused in writing. On the 21st of May
2024, he
wrote: “Only by
police direct or order the MCST to disclose the footage that MCST is obliged
to do so.” That is not what PDPC’s own
guidelines say. The guidelines for management corporations say access may
not be limited only to enforcement agencies, such as the police. I wrote
back, citing those guidelines. The DPO’s reply: “It
seems to me you are having difficulty understanding our position.” And he
refused to communicate with me further.
Neither condominium cited a single ground from the law. The PDPA lists the
only legal reasons a request can be refused —
section 21, subsection 3, and the 5th
Schedule. Privacy as a blanket reason is not on that
list. Police-only
access is not on that list. And
later, the short recording from Suites@Cairnhill, the
1 I had taken only because staff helped me, was
used by PDPC to
say the footage was not personal data.
While I was trying to find out who managed the building, the
clock was running. At
1st, I was
told the footage was kept for many months. That was my
understanding. So when
Knight Frank later said no
footage had been captured, I became alarmed.
Because I knew that was not true.
Security guards had already identified the footage. They had
described what happened. That was when I
began to suspect the problem was not that the footage did not exist. The
problem was that
access could be denied until the footage disappeared. A
new management team later claimed the retention cycle was 20 to 30
days. PDPC
eventually said 17 days, and
accepted that figure without verifying it. 17 days. That was the
window. And that
date mattered. PDPC later
treated Knight Frank’s request to the MCST as the access-request date. Then
it
treated the auto-deletion as happening before the MCST’s
formal refusal. Under that
logic, section 22 A
became useless. The
footage could disappear during the
live access process, and deletion was still not treated as a breach. I was
still
trying to find out the company name on day 4. So I did what the
law says to do. I
filed a formal complaint with the Personal Data Protection Commission. For
The Scotts
Tower, I explained the verbal refusal on April 17th, my
written follow-up on April 20-5th, the
missing company name, the missing DPO contact, and the
claim that no footage had been captured. At that point, I did not
know PDPC would
later say the footage had already been overwritten on April thirtieth. What
I did
know was this: the
footage had been identified. Knight Frank’s “no footage” claim was false.
And I was
worried that The Scotts Tower MCST or
Knight Frank could deny access by letting the video disappear. I
told PDPC that. PDPC did not
preserve or verify the more direct front footage. Instead, I was
told to go to the police. Only after that did I
try the other angle from Suites@Cairnhill. When its
managing agent refused on the “police-only”
ground, I filed that complaint with PDPC as
well. And then.
Nothing meaningful. No
preservation action. No
verification. Instead, PDPC
came up with reasons on behalf of the condominiums, without checking the
core facts. And none of those reasons addressed what the condominiums had
actually said. The Scotts
Tower had said privacy, then no
footage. Suites@Cairnhill had said police-only
access. Months
passed. Eventually, there was a
response, but not the
1 the law seemed to promise. My
Member of Parliament intervened. Twice. PDPC did not
move. I appealed. PDPC did not
change its position. Not on
privacy. Not on “police-only.” Not on
deletion. After I
proved the data had been deleted, and the police
confirmed they had no
video either, PDPC’s only
deflection had run out. They had no other
reasons to reject me. What they did
instead was open some kind of investigation into
TST’s data deletion. I do not
know which obligation it was opened under. I do not know what they
looked at. I just know it was not the
right I had asked about. That is the
pattern. The right to
retrieve my own data was treated as not worth investigating. The
deletion of that same data, after it was
gone, was treated as worth investigating.
Eventually, PDPC
issued its findings. 2 cases. 2
sets of reasoning. For Suites@Cairnhill, they
said the CCTV footage did not contain “personal data.” Here is how they
made that determination. They
relied on my own evidence — a short handphone recording of the CCTV screen,
taken at the management office, after staff had helped me view what their
camera captured. That
recording existed because staff helped me. I did not disclose that
earlier help when I later made the formal request, because I did not want
to get the staff into trouble. But
later, PDPC
used the recording against me. PDPC
said the rider was only a
silhouette. No
facial features. No
motorcycle licence plate. Therefore, not personal data. But that is not
what the
statute says. The PDPA does not
say a face or licence plate must be visible. It
defines personal data as data about an
individual who can be
identified from that data or from that data and other
information. And there was other information. The
guards had identified the footage within minutes. The
request gave the date, time, place, and who I was. The
whole reason I was asking was because that camera captured my accident.
Identifiability. Not clarity. This is the
moment to understand. PDPC
took my own evidence. Used it against me. And the
test they applied — the clarity test — does not
exist in the legislation. It was
invented. By the
regulator. To dismiss my case. In
football, there is a
famous goal scored by Diego Maradona — his
hand made contact with the ball. The referee missed it. The
goal stood. Afterwards, Maradona called it “the hand of God.” PDPC’s
clarity test is the regulatory equivalent. They scored a goal with
something never in the rules. The
legal test was identifiability. They
replaced it with visual clarity. Then they
declared victory. And moved on.
Let me show you what PDPC did,
side by side.
1st condominium — Suites@Cairnhill. The
DPO said: “Only by police direct/order the
MCST to disclose the footage.” PDPC
said: “The footage
contains no personal data.” The condominium never said that. PDPC
invented that reason for them.
2nd condominium — The Scotts Tower. I
made a verbal request on April 17th. I was
refused on privacy grounds, and given no DPO contact, no company name, no
escalation path. On
April 20-5th, I
followed up in writing. When
challenged, they
later claimed no footage existed. That was
false — PDPC’s own
decision says the footage existed until April thirtieth. But PDPC’s
preservation analysis did not
give legal weight to either of those earlier events. Not the
April 17th verbal refusal by the managing agent. Not my April 20-5th
written access
request. Instead, the timeline shifted to what happened inside the condominium:
the
managing agent asked the MCST on April 20-9th. The
footage was overwritten on April thirtieth. The
formal refusal came on May 2nd. That is the
twist. My request disappears. The
managing agent’s earlier refusal disappears. The
false “no
footage” statement disappears. The warning that the footage might be deleted
disappears. And
s.22A becomes useless, because deletion before the formal refusal
becomes no breach. In both
cases, PDPC
substituted its own reasoning for what the
condominiums actually said. And in
neither case did they test the actual stated grounds against the law. Section
21, subsection 3, together with the 5th Schedule — these are
the only
provisions that authorise an organisation to
lawfully refuse an access
request. “Privacy” is not listed. “Police-only” is not listed. PDPC
never even checked. I
wrote to PDPC with 9
questions. Specific, legal questions across 6 sections of the PDPA. Which
section authorises the
clarity test? Why were the condominiums’ actual reasons never tested against
the 5th Schedule? Why did the April 17th verbal refusal not matter?
Why did my April 20-5th written request not trigger preservation before
the footage disappeared? Why did “many months,” what security told me,
become 17 days? Why was a request handled by the
managing agent treated as legally different from the
MCST’s own responsibility, when section 4, subsection 2 removes most
direct obligations from a data intermediary, and section 4, subsection
3 puts the same obligation
back on the organisation as if it
processed the data itself? Those questions were never
answered. There was a repeated line: “The Guidelines are not determinative.
The PDPA takes precedence.” But that does not answer the question. It does
not
say which guideline. It does not say which section of the
PDPA. It does not say what the
conflict is. And when
PDPC did try to answer a limited point, like the definition of personal
data, they did not
explain the original reasoning. They
introduced a new idea:
reasonableness. As if
identifiability depends on whether it is reasonable to identify me from
the
footage. But the security guards had already found the footage within minutes.
They
knew the date. They knew the time. They knew the location. They knew who
was
asking. That is the real-world
identifiability that PDPC ignored. The
written findings were eventually released. When I posted
questions on the reasoning, PDPC did not answer on the merits. Months later,
more reasonings appeared, including a “reasonableness” gloss on
identifiability, without explaining the original gap.
PDPC also declined to
publish the report online promptly. That only happened after I escalated.
On June 20-3rd, 2025, PDPC wrote: “Decisions and undertakings
are generally published on the microsite
within the year. We are unable to commit to a fixed date at this point.”
So the
public could not see the reasoning. My
questions were not answered on the merits. The findings were not promptly
on the public record. And
PDPC treated the matter as closed. But the
TST investigation had
already proven that the data had been deleted. That was no
longer in dispute. Even so, the
officer handling my case continued with flawed reasonings for my Suites
complaint, closing it on the
basis that it was similar to TST. That could not
stand. TST was
wrong. Saying Suites was similar to a wrong decision was not a reason at
all. I
asked for the decision to be
reopened. What I
got in return was rude and unbecoming behavior expected of a civil servant.
I did not
want to complain about PDPC. I
went there because I needed my footage. In
September 2024, I
escalated to IMDA. I
emailed Mr Lew Chuen Hong,
IMDA’s Chief Executive. I
copied the PDPC Commissioner. And
because I did not know which department would handle my feedback, I
sent the email to 3 IMDA branches at the same time. The complaint ran
for 11 months. I
sent 12 emails. The
last was on the 14th of
August 2025. During the
IMDA investigation, my complaint was leaked back to the PDPC officers under
review. On the 20th of August 2025,
Ms Yeong Wan Ling, IMDA’s Head of Internal Audit, wrote to me. Her
finding:
PDPC and its officers “did not commit any wrongful practices.” She
endorsed PDPC’s reasoning. She
said PDPC had directed me to inform the police — to avoid interfering with
police
investigations. That was her
stated rationale for why nothing was wrong. That rationale does not
exist in the PDPA. The only
grounds for refusing access are section 21, subsection 3, and
the 5th
Schedule. “Active
police investigation” is not listed. It was an
excuse. IMDA endorsed it. IMDA also
said PDPC had “acted in accordance with its protocols.” And it identified
“certain areas of improvement” — without naming them. The
findings were “final and conclusive.” The investigation was closed. By this
point, I stopped asking whether my case was handled wrongly. I started asking
a different question. How
many cases like mine has PDPC ever found a breach on? PDPC’s
website used to let you filter enforcement decisions by obligation type.
At some
point, that filter disappeared. So I
went through the entire register myself. Every decision. Every
finding. 384
cases, compiled as of June 2026. The Access Obligation — section
21 of the PDPA, the right of a citizen to access their own
personal data — has produced 0 breach findings. 0.
Across 384
published enforcement actions. Not 1. The
dominant pattern of PDPC enforcement is data protection and consent — organisations
mishandling data they
hold. The right of a citizen to retrieve their own data from an organisation?
That is the
least enforced provision in the entire register. Across those 3 hundred
and eighty-4
cases, only
2 involve a complainant demanding access to their own CCTV data and being
refused. Both are mine. Both from the same
accident on Cairnhill
Road. Both dismissed without a finding that the Access Obligation was breached.
The
clarity test explains this. If face or licence
plate must be visible for CCTV footage to qualify as personal data — and
that
standard exists nowhere in the statute — then
any organisation can deny an access
request by asserting the footage is too unclear. And the Complainant has
no
tools to challenge that assertion. After the 1986
World Cup quarter-final,
Maradona was asked about his goal. He
said: “It was a little
bit the hand of God, and a little bit the
head of Maradona.” Not
quite admitting. Not quite
denying. PDPC’s 1-line reply — “The
Guidelines are not determinative; the PDPA takes precedence” — to 9 legal
questions about the merits. Same energy. They cannot say what really happened.
So they
give the same non-answer to each question, and declare the file closed.
Here is what I have
learned, going through every document, every decision, every response. Ordinary
regulatory failure is uneven. Mistakes in different
directions. Inconsistent outcomes. Different responses to different challenges.
What is documented here — across 2 PDPC cases, an
IMDA review,
9 legal questions, 384 enforcement actions
— is not uneven. Every decision. At every level. In the same direction.
PDPC invented reasoning for the condominiums. IMDA stamped “no wrongful
practices” without opening the envelope. 9 legal questions got 1 line.
0 breach findings across 384
cases. This is the
shape of a policy. Not necessarily an explicit
1. Nobody needs to have written it down. Here is the
principle that distinguishes enforcement discretion from what happened here.
Any
body can
decide to actively enforce something, or not, according to the circumstances
of the day. That is a
regulator’s discretion. What no
body can do is
actively decide to deny the rights of a citizen or resident, and
reinterpret the law to protect the perpetrators of that denial. That is
what
happened here. An
active decision to deny — and an active decision to
invent grounds to justify the denial. The
clarity test is the legal mechanism. The 0-breach
history is the outcome. The
non-engagement is what follows when a regulator cannot defend its position
on the merits. I built a
site. pdpaaccessrights.sg.
Every document is there. Both PDPC
decisions — the
1 that found “no personal data” using my own handphone
video, and the 1 that reframed a deleted-footage
case as an accountability breach. The
parliamentary answer from Minister Teo
promising preservation and penalties — next to what happened in my case.
The 9 legal questions and the same 1-line reply. The
enforcement register analysis — 384
cases, 0 access obligation breach findings. The
timeline. The contradictions. The
documented failures. Everything on that site comes from a PDPC decision,
the
PDPA statute, a
parliamentary record, or correspondence in my
possession. Nothing is
asserted that is not sourced. Every claim has a footnote. Every source is
primary. The
evidence is public. You can
check it yourself. I am not a
lawyer. I am not an
MP. I am a
citizen who asked for footage of an accident that erased his memory, and
found that the right the law promised me did not exist in practice. The
Access Obligation has produced 0 breach findings across over a decade
of PDPC enforcement. 0. Across 384
published cases. If a
statutory right has never been enforced — not once — is it being enforced
at all? And if not — by what
mechanism, and by whom, is it being rendered unenforceable? All the evidence
is at pdpaaccessrights.sg. Check it yourself.